<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Twelve hour entrepreneur]]></title><description><![CDATA[A starter blog demonstrating what Gatsby can do.]]></description><link>https://www.twelvehourentrepreneur.com</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 May 2021 10:19:51 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Validating a new SaaS idea]]></title><description><![CDATA[Don’t start with the idea, start with the problem Stupidly, at the start I fell in love with the “idea” of being able to annotate web pages…]]></description><link>https://www.twelvehourentrepreneur.com/validating-a-business-idea-for-a-new-saas/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.twelvehourentrepreneur.com/validating-a-business-idea-for-a-new-saas/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 13:06:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h3&gt;Don’t start with the idea, start with the problem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stupidly, at the start I fell in love with the “idea” of being able to annotate web pages with comments / feedback and tried to retrofit the feature into existing problem spaces like customer feedback and digital agency tools. I even bought the domain &lt;a href=&quot;http://annotately.io/&quot;&gt;annotately.io&lt;/a&gt; thinking the product was set in stone and all was left was to validate it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thankfully I realised the idea was terrible, I discovered this by doing market research and working on my value propositions. The best exercise I did was building the landing page first (i.e. the packaging) and working backwards to the product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s the steps I took to get to my landing page:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. Market research&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not going to pretend to be an expert in validating how much a specific market is worth or who owns what share of said market - I didn’t dig that far. What I did do was come up with a list of competitors in a similar space, looked them up on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.g2.com/&quot;&gt;g2.com&lt;/a&gt; and made some lists:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What customers would &lt;em&gt;expect&lt;/em&gt; as standard:&lt;/strong&gt; I looked up all the positive reviews and grouped the common stuff into a list of features customers would expect as standard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How I could differentiate:&lt;/strong&gt; I looked up all the negative reviews and made a list of the things missing from existing products. This was how I could be &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; or how I could position myself differently for an under-served niche.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How my product experience could be better:&lt;/strong&gt; I signed up for free trials for all competitor products. This gave me a feel for how they on-boarded users and what features they focussed on. Seeing how average some products were also helped ease some doubt that I was too far behind building a product from scratch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How I could &lt;em&gt;sell&lt;/em&gt; my product:&lt;/strong&gt; I looked up all the competitor landing pages to see what language they were using to describe their products and what their core value propositions were. This again gave me ideas on how to position myself &lt;em&gt;differently&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. Come up with my core value propositions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the above lists, I came up with a rough list of features and converted them to value propositions using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.julian.com/guide/growth/landing-pages&quot;&gt;Julian Shapiro’s guide&lt;/a&gt;. This was &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; time consuming, but it was worth it as I avoided getting tunnel vision on ideas and building things no one wants. The exercise helped me realise some of those features didn’t have a corresponding benefit and they got killed in favour of better ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3. Design and build a landing page&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously this part is more straight forward:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I used &lt;a href=&quot;figma.com&quot;&gt;Figma&lt;/a&gt; to come up with mockups first. I used to just build the page and keep tweaking the CSS until I was happy, but from experience found there’s a lot of waste with that workflow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gatsbyjs.com/&quot;&gt;Gatsby&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://tailwindcss.com/&quot;&gt;Tailwind CSS&lt;/a&gt; to build the page. For anyone that doesn’t know Tailwind it’s worth checking out for the time it saves making pages responsive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I used Google Tag Manager to set up &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.google/products/marketingplatform/analytics/new_google_analytics/&quot;&gt;GA4&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hotjar.com/&quot;&gt;Hotjar&lt;/a&gt;. GA4 will help me get insights into the SEM keywords that are driving the highest converting users on my page. Hotjar will help me discover where people are engaged and where they’re dropping off.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4. Set the first milestone&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I need to figure what my distribution channels are and &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; I can reach my target customers. I’ll start with SEM to test the cost of acquisition but I’m going to test some alternatives like &lt;a href=&quot;https://betalist.com/&quot;&gt;Betalist&lt;/a&gt; (although I’m not expecting high quality leads from there).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Milestone #1: Interview 10 users in my target market&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Lessons from 5 failed side hustles]]></title><description><![CDATA[I’ve built 5 failed side hustles over 10 years and my biggest regret isn’t that I failed, it’s that I didn’t fail faster. I’m starting over…]]></description><link>https://www.twelvehourentrepreneur.com/lessons-from-5-failed-side-hustles/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.twelvehourentrepreneur.com/lessons-from-5-failed-side-hustles/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Apr 2021 20:23:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’ve built 5 failed side hustles over 10 years and my biggest regret isn’t that I failed, it’s that I didn’t fail faster. I’m starting over with &lt;a href=&quot;https://usertake.com&quot;&gt;usertake.com&lt;/a&gt; but before I do I’m looking back over &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; the others failed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Failure #1: Cosmic Badger&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;What was it?&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=P7CrEEZGkeA&amp;#x26;ab_channel=CosmicBadger&quot;&gt;Trailer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An auto-runner platformer game for iOS and Android. I started building it as a side project to learn Javascript but near the end of the project &lt;em&gt;believed&lt;/em&gt; that it could make money. The game did not sell well but in hindsight, I’m surprised it sold anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Some vanity metrics&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;160 units sold&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~$160 revenue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~2 years development time of evening and weekends. Th majority of work was photoshopping tilesheets, level design, coding was the easy part&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Some &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; metrics&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hourly wage: ~$0.08c&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;What I thought to be true when I started&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t think a game like this has been made before, I think it’s got an interesting hook and people might pay for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;What I thought to be true after it failed&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People aren’t prepared to pay for apps with maybe the exception of utility apps. If I want to make money from making mobile games it has to be free, it has to be &lt;em&gt;highly&lt;/em&gt; polished and it has to be remarkable. That’s the only way to compete in a saturated app store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Failure #2: The Senario Game&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;What was it?&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.badgerdigital.the.scenario.game&amp;#x26;hl=en_AU&amp;#x26;gl=US&quot;&gt;Link to App&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Scenario-based “Would you rather” game for iOS and Android. This project started as a way to test the market for a much more ambitious project that never materialised. It’s gone from the app store now because it wasn’t making enough money to justify paying my Apple developer license, or justifying the hoops I had to jump through maintaining Facebook SDK updates or supporting a mandatory Apple login implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By some sheer luck event, this app caught the attention of a major casual mobile app publisher. They ran some tests on it for retention and marketability. It failed those tests so nothing more was done with this app. I did propose a new app for them to test though, which is failure #3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Some vanity metrics&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;19.5k installs on iOS, 3.4k installs on Android&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1M app store search impressions with an app impression-to-install conversion rate of 2.1%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Average rating of 4.6 on Android&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can’t remember the rating on iOS but it was around 4.3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Some &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; metrics&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~$6 in ad revenue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Currently 6 daily active users&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roughly 18 months of work to build, evenings and weekends. This included some wasted time pivoting ideas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;What I thought to be true when I started&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I can create an app with user generated content and build an active community around it then my user based will grow organically and I can make money from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;What I thought to be true after it failed&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building an app for a casual market is &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; hard. I have no idea what users are looking for because I’m not my app’s target market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Failure #3: Yes or No&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;What was it?&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.producthunt.com/posts/yes-or-no-2&quot;&gt;Link to Product Hunt Page&lt;/a&gt; - no longer on the app store&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I simple Yes or No questions game for iOS with a Tinder style swipe-to-answer system. As mentioned above, the same publisher that contacted me for The Scenario Game agreed to run the same acquisition tests for Yes or No. Marketability was much better but it still failed on retention. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Some vanity metrics&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11.5k installs on iOS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;693k app store search impressions with an app impression-to-install conversion rate of 2.1%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Some &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; metrics&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~$12 in ad revenue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Currently 1 daily active user (not me), even though it’s no longer on the app store.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roughly 3 months of work to build, evenings and weekends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;What I thought to be true when I started&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I can build an app that is marketable, has high retention and a low cost of acquisition I can partner with a publisher to acquire users at scale and make a decent income.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;What I thought to be true after it failed&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B2C is for dreamers and businesses with loads of capital. It’s much easier to make money building B2B software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Failure #4: Prioritsely&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;What was it?&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A tool that allowed remote teams to &lt;strong&gt;prioritise&lt;/strong&gt; Kanban wall tasks asynchronously. I built a prototype and reached out to remote product managers over Twitter and LinkedIn to organise some interviews and prototype testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn’t spend longer than a month or two working on this project and it made no money. I consider it one of my most successful side projects because I quickly realised it wasn’t worth building and avoided months of wasted time. I was pragmatic enough to interview about 10 different people in my target market to gain insights into if the tool would be useful. What I concluded in the end was I had a feature, not a product. To build a product I’d need to build a project management SaaS, which was suicide so I killed it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Some vanity metrics&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10 product managers /  scrum leads interviewed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Some &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; metrics&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hourly wage $0 p/h&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;What I thought to be true when I started&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have no idea if this idea is worth pursuing, I need to build a rough prototype and do some user testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;What I thought to be true after it failed&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This idea isn’t worth pursuing, I’m glad I did user testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Failure #5: Bookly&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;What was it?&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://booklyapp.com/&quot;&gt;Link to website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A crowd-sourced library for your organisations, in Slack. I jumped right into to building this with no validation because I convinced myself that it would be fun to make and that it “scratched my own itch”. If I factor out the work I put in then it’s making a modest amount of passive income.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried gaining users through cold outreach over Twitter and LinkedIn but it was too hard. All my current customers are organic through the Slack store but it ultimately failed because it was too hard to scale. People aren’t actively searching for a solution for this. Most people don’t even have this problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though it didn’t make me a substantial amount of money, this was the project that made me believe it’s actually possible to make a living building a SaaS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Some vanity metrics&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~80 organic installs from the Slack app store. This is for the free trial, you start paying after reaching a book limit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Some &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; metrics&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$937 in revenue in total so far&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Makes about $70 MRR right now, it was making more but I lost a customer because their office went remote due to Covid&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hourly wage ~$2.30 p/h&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roughly 3-4 months of work evenings and weekends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Activation rates are really poor, probably less than 5%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;What I thought to be true when I started&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven’t validated this at all but it might be fun to make and shouldn’t take that long to build&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;What I thought to be true after it failed&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trying to build something new and unique is too hard and risky, I should stick to a known problem in a boring market&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What do I think to be true now?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t regret any of these failures, I can see how far I’ve come from learning these hard lessons but my god it wears you down. I’m now focussing on &lt;a href=&quot;https://usertake.com&quot;&gt;usertake.com&lt;/a&gt; and this time I want to be as pragmatic as possible and not blindly guessing what the outcome might be, here’s what I think&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solving an existing problem in a validated market is boring, but who cares? My goal is to make a sustainable living, not change the world. If I can build a fake landing page for a product that &lt;strong&gt;positions itself differently&lt;/strong&gt; to competitors, &lt;strong&gt;reach&lt;/strong&gt; my target audience through a &lt;strong&gt;cheap enough distribution channel&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;understand a common pain&lt;/strong&gt; they all want solved then I can build an MVP and change course from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Why build a SaaS and share revenue in public?]]></title><description><![CDATA[I’ve built five failed side hustles in ten years. Every time I had a new idea I had the same fear that someone would steal it, so I decided…]]></description><link>https://www.twelvehourentrepreneur.com/why-build-a-saas-and-share-revenue-in-public/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.twelvehourentrepreneur.com/why-build-a-saas-and-share-revenue-in-public/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 20:36:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’ve built five failed side hustles in ten years. Every time I had a new idea I had the same fear that someone would steal it, so I decided to build in a vacuum until release. Looking back, no one was going to steal my idea because they were all flawed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may well be my last side project, and if I’m going to build something flawed again I’d rather find out sooner and change direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Focus on the process not the outcome&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest mistakes I made with my other projects was having this vision of an end goal and using that as fuel to keep me going. I’d say to myself “the sooner I focus and build this, the quicker I can make money”, but I missed checking in on the milestones to see if it was &lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt; going to make money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog is about the &lt;strong&gt;process&lt;/strong&gt; of building a SaaS rather than details specific to my product. I’ll talk about things like competitor research, landing pages, positioning, validation, user interviews, metrics, distribution, and probably a lots of other stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why build in public&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading Twitter recently it seems like I’m late to the party with the build-in-public movement, but I was inspired to do this from reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.navalmanack.com/&quot;&gt;The Almanack of Naval Ravikant&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more desire I have for something to work out a certain way, the less likely I am to see the truth. Especially in business, if something isn’t going well, I try to acknowledge it publicly and I try to acknowledge it publicly in front of my co-founders and friends and co-workers. Then, I’m not hiding it from anybody
else. If I’m not hiding it from anybody, I’m not going to delude myself from what’s actually going on - &lt;em&gt;Naval&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s a few of the reasons I’m documenting my ideas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;1. Clearer thinking&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only does becoming a better writer help become a better thinker, but documenting my thoughts keeps me honest about my progress. With previous projects when I internalised my thoughts it was easy to sidestep problems with other more manageable ideas when there was any resistance. Writing for an audience forces me to address questions I know others will ask.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;2. Shared experiences&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m sure there’s a lot of people in the same boat right now. I hope some of the things I write about are useful to others but equally I hope there are people a few steps ahead of me pointing out ideas that won’t work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;3. Consistency&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s another idea from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/naval&quot;&gt;Naval&lt;/a&gt; but I’m sure it’s taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com.au/Influence-Psychology-Persuasion-Business-Essentials-ebook/dp/B002BD2UUC&quot;&gt;Influence: The psychology of persuasion&lt;/a&gt;. People want to be consistent with what they say so the more people I tell about my ideas, the more chance I’ll be to follow through with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;4. Connecting with like-minded makers&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a maker is tough. When things are going well you’re energised and happy to keep going. When things are going badly it’s a lonely void of dispair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I honestly wish I had more people to talk to at the same stage as me to share war stories. If any of this resonates with you then feel free to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cosmic_badger&quot;&gt;reach out on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;5. Social Proof&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I see someone tweet they reached $100 MRR I’m already intrigued. I’ll click their profile and see what they’re selling. If I someone making over $1,000 MRR and documenting their experiences I’ll follow them straight away. Knowing people are paying even a small amount for your SaaS tells people your service is valuable. Knowing people are paying a lot for your SaaS tells people your &lt;em&gt;ideas&lt;/em&gt; are valuable.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>