<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: sketch | The story of Cosmic Badger]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/categories/sketch/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-03T18:43:22+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Reilly]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bringing sketches to life]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/2015/03/20/bringing-game-dev-sketches-to-life/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-20T22:57:13+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/2015/03/20/bringing-game-dev-sketches-to-life</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There&rsquo;s nothing more satisfying as an indie dev than sketching down an idea and then implementing that idea in your game world. In this post I wanted to pay tribute to some of the earlier sketches and how they turned out, being implemented in the Cosmic Badger universe.</p>

<p>The grass stage were the first levels that I worked on. I had very little experience as a &ldquo;pixel artist&rdquo; at this point and I actually went through a couple of iterations of the sprites before I got it to a state that I was happy with. I&rsquo;ll cover some of those in another blog.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/grass_stage.jpg' width='' height='' title='Concept art for the grass themed stage'><span class='caption-text'>Concept art for the grass themed stage</span></span></p>

<p>The industrial stage took a day or two to complete the background for. I hadn&rsquo;t really gotten a grasp on gradients at this stage and was changing the variation in shadow manually by changing the brightness/contrast. Everything was very much a learning process.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/industrial_stage.jpg' width='' height='' title='Concept art for the industrial themed stage'><span class='caption-text'>Concept art for the industrial themed stage</span></span></p>

<p>Despite its simplicity, the toy stage came out as one of the best. The varying colours made it much more of an interesting level, landscape-wise. Some of the sketches were crudley drawn and then done properly from scratch on computer, others were scanned and then inked.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/toy_stage.jpg' width='' height='' title='Concept art for the toy stage. Some of these sprites are still a little rough as I never re-touched them later. I&rsquo;ll get to them.'><span class='caption-text'>Concept art for the toy stage. Some of these sprites are still a little rough as I never re-touched them later. I&rsquo;ll get to them.</span></span></p>

<p>The black and white levels were some of the hardest to get just right. The foreground obstacles had to contrast enough from the background to be visible but that&rsquo;s kind of hard when you&rsquo;re working with the different tones of the same colour all the time.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/black_and_white_stage.jpg' width='' height='' title='This came out as one of my favourites'><span class='caption-text'>This came out as one of my favourites</span></span></p>

<p>How much has your own concept art reflected your final game? Could it still be improved or are you happy with the results?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
