<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: html5 | The story of Cosmic Badger]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/categories/html5/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-30T21:14:50+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Reilly]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Back from sabbatical]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/2015/08/30/back-from-sabbatical/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-30T20:01:46+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/2015/08/30/back-from-sabbatical</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For anyone following previous posts, you may have noticed a distinct lack of activity for a long time. This has mainly come down to a couple things:</p>

<p><strong> 1. Launch Frenzy </strong></p>

<p>Launching a game is stressful business, you gotta create press kits, draft press emails, register as a business owner, taxes and a whole lot of other boring adult stuff.</p>

<p><strong> 2. Burnout </strong></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve spent the good part of two years plugging away at this little project on evenings and weekends. I&rsquo;ve missed an Australian Summer (as an Irish person, that&rsquo;s quite a sacrifice) confined to a text editor, chasing the idea of seeing a game through to completion. When I had the realisation that I wasn&rsquo;t an overnight millionaire post-launch, I decided to take a step back and enjoy my freedom for a while.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve finally been able to read again, play video games (I might finally complete GTA) and staying out late on a weekend. While all of this has been great, there&rsquo;s unfinished business. I&rsquo;ve created a playable game and have received some good [albeit mixed in a few circumstances] feedback on it but it&rsquo;s still missing some finishing touches. It&rsquo;s time to give it one last go before moving on to new projects.</p>

<p>More blog posts coming soon!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Indie Games Festival - post-mortem]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/2015/04/03/indie-games-festival/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-03T16:00:47+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/2015/04/03/indie-games-festival</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last Saturday I had the opportunity to showcase my game to the public for the first time. A few days before I was looking through gamedev posts on reddit and stumbled across a post about open spots for iFest, a free-to-the-public independent game festival in Melbourne. Now I&rsquo;ve never heard anything about the event before, there was next to no press for it and a worrying lack of followers on the official Twitter page so I assumed that it was going to be pretty small-time. It was no PAX for sure; but showcasing here offered a couple of opportunities:</p>

<p><strong> 1. Publicity </strong></p>

<p>Raise a little more awareness about the game and gain a few more followers on Twitter / Facebook</p>

<p><strong> 2. Feedback </strong></p>

<p>Up until this point, the only people that had played or tested the game were friends or colleagues. I&rsquo;m not saying that they aren&rsquo;t capable of giving constructive feedback but first impressions from random punters are going to be a lot more honest, and more accurately reflect the initial reaction once the game goes live on the app stores.</p>

<p><strong> Preparation </strong></p>

<p>The timing was actually pretty bad. I had no paraphernalia or expensive, flashy banners and with a couple of days to prepare <em>and</em> a house move happening on the same weekend the stand wasn&rsquo;t going to be the most professional of displays. It was literally a few hours to mock up some pretty crude posters from existing in-game assets with some social media links on them and rushing to OfficeWorks to get it all printed. The result came out at AU$60 for posters to hang off my stand, 150 business cards (cut up by hand from A4 card prints the night before) and a t-shirt, because that&rsquo;s how professionals roll.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/paraphernalia.jpg' width='' height='' title='What 3 hours accomplishes in paraphernalia'><span class='caption-text'>What 3 hours accomplishes in paraphernalia</span></span></p>

<p><strong> The event </strong></p>

<p>I arrived at iFest around 10am, just in time for it to open to the public and expectations were pretty much accurate. There were about 20 stands there, some of which were flashier than others depending on the studio. I happened to be placed next to a small indie team of five, some of which were ex-EA developers. They were working on a Kickstarter called <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=POzlC6aTfPs">Space Dust Racers</a>. Their setup was pretty decent compared to what I was about to pullout of the bag. They had a big widescreen TV with multiple X-Box controllers but most importantly, they had a <em>really</em> polished, playable game. It looked closer to a AAA studio game than indie, which made me quite nervous about setting up my stand and how small-time it might look in comparison to others.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/iFest.jpg' width='' height='' title='iFest at Federation Square in Melbourne'><span class='caption-text'>iFest at Federation Square in Melbourne</span></span></p>

<p>I had a shitty old 13&#8221; monitor (which I never even ended up using, partly because of embarrassment) and my MacBook Air for showing my first-cut launch trailer. I fired that up, plopped a test device down on the table with a couple of stacks of business cards. The first half of the day was a slow trickle of people walking through the event, some of which had no idea what the festival actually was. It got busier after lunch time but overall I had only about 30-40 people visit my stand over the course of the 4.5 hours there, which pretty much representative of the event itself.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/iFest-stand.jpg' width='' height='' title='The lemonade stand - we all have to start somewhere'><span class='caption-text'>The lemonade stand - we all have to start somewhere</span></span></p>

<p><strong> Public reaction </strong></p>

<p>So my Twitter following wasn&rsquo;t really going to take off. As uneventful as the day was, none of that really mattered because once people started approaching my stand (no matter how small in number) and started playing my game it really changed my perspective of my own game. I got a range of different demographics from parents and children to software undergrads but pretty much everyone seemed to really enjoy playing <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L6zrbYjWO0c">Cosmic Badger</a>. I saw people smile while playing the game, or laughing when the game mechanic finally clicked - that &ldquo;Ah!&rdquo; moment that I wanted people to figure out on their own. Some kept playing for 5-10 minutes at a time, one guy even came back for a second go half an hour later.</p>

<p>Some slightly paraphrased quotes from memory:</p>

<p><strong> Positive feedback </strong></p>

<ul>
<li>&ldquo;that was actually fun&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;that&rsquo;s a really cool mechanic, I don&rsquo;t think that&rsquo;s ever been done before&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;I can see myself getting addicted after a while&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;I love the pastel colour art-style&rdquo;</li>
</ul>


<p><strong> Constructive feedback </strong></p>

<ul>
<li>&ldquo;Some of the obstacles look like they&rsquo;re in the background&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;Needs some cooler space / time rift effect between the portals&rdquo;</li>
</ul>


<p><strong> Questions </strong></p>

<ul>
<li>&ldquo;So it&rsquo;s portal meets flappy bird?&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;Why a badger?&rdquo;</li>
</ul>


<p>The things I felt when I first started playing my initial prototype (before the two years worth of work where I had become completely impartial), the things that I wanted others to experience when they picked up the game and started playing were happening, and this was one of the most satisfying and reassuring moments since starting this project.</p>

<p>Most of us indie devs spend months to years working on our own pet projects. During which we constantly doubt ourselves and our abilities, and become almost apathetic to what we&rsquo;re working on. Some of us have seen and played so much of our own game that it&rsquo;s hard to tell if it&rsquo;s actually good any more. Getting strangers&#8217; feedback was one of the most important realisations in this project.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m hoping to submit my game for app store review this weekend. When it finally releases I have no idea how many people will download it, or even realise it&rsquo;s out there, but at least last weekend I realised that I&rsquo;ve accomplished something. I&rsquo;ve finished a game, someone played it and someone liked it.</p>

<p><strong> Special Mentions </strong></p>

<p>I want to give  a special mention to the two stands each side of me, one which was hobby dev <a href="http://hemingwaygames.com/">Hemmingway Games</a> like me, taking every opportunity outside of his day job to work on his passion. The other is the kickstarter team of 5 working on <a href="http://www.spaceduststudios.com/">Space Dust Racers</a>, who have really earned my respect. They quit their full-time jobs while supporting families to work on their own vision. Asking for a modest amount on Kickstarter, these guys seem more focussed on achieving their goal and earning enough to survive than being greedy. I&rsquo;ve played their game and it was actually really fun, so check them out when they launch.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bringing sketches to life]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/2015/03/20/bringing-game-dev-sketches-to-life/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-20T22:57:13+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/2015/03/20/bringing-game-dev-sketches-to-life</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There&rsquo;s nothing more satisfying as an indie dev than sketching down an idea and then implementing that idea in your game world. In this post I wanted to pay tribute to some of the earlier sketches and how they turned out, being implemented in the Cosmic Badger universe.</p>

<p>The grass stage were the first levels that I worked on. I had very little experience as a &ldquo;pixel artist&rdquo; at this point and I actually went through a couple of iterations of the sprites before I got it to a state that I was happy with. I&rsquo;ll cover some of those in another blog.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/grass_stage.jpg' width='' height='' title='Concept art for the grass themed stage'><span class='caption-text'>Concept art for the grass themed stage</span></span></p>

<p>The industrial stage took a day or two to complete the background for. I hadn&rsquo;t really gotten a grasp on gradients at this stage and was changing the variation in shadow manually by changing the brightness/contrast. Everything was very much a learning process.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/industrial_stage.jpg' width='' height='' title='Concept art for the industrial themed stage'><span class='caption-text'>Concept art for the industrial themed stage</span></span></p>

<p>Despite its simplicity, the toy stage came out as one of the best. The varying colours made it much more of an interesting level, landscape-wise. Some of the sketches were crudley drawn and then done properly from scratch on computer, others were scanned and then inked.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/toy_stage.jpg' width='' height='' title='Concept art for the toy stage. Some of these sprites are still a little rough as I never re-touched them later. I&rsquo;ll get to them.'><span class='caption-text'>Concept art for the toy stage. Some of these sprites are still a little rough as I never re-touched them later. I&rsquo;ll get to them.</span></span></p>

<p>The black and white levels were some of the hardest to get just right. The foreground obstacles had to contrast enough from the background to be visible but that&rsquo;s kind of hard when you&rsquo;re working with the different tones of the same colour all the time.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/black_and_white_stage.jpg' width='' height='' title='This came out as one of my favourites'><span class='caption-text'>This came out as one of my favourites</span></span></p>

<p>How much has your own concept art reflected your final game? Could it still be improved or are you happy with the results?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Level design of an indie game]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/2015/02/26/designing-levels-for-a-2d-platformer/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-26T20:36:37+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/2015/02/26/designing-levels-for-a-2d-platformer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Designing your game is probably one of the most crucial parts of the game development lifecycle. It&rsquo;s an iterative process, for sure, but design documents have to start somewhere. In this post I&rsquo;m going to talk about the initial designs of the levels in Cosmic Badger and the inception of the tilesheets used in the game to date.</p>

<p>With a <a href="/2015/02/15/knowing-when-to-cut-the-scope-of-your-indie-game/">clearer vision</a> of how the game would look, it was now time to start designing the levels. There was no real complex workflow to this. I bought a load of graph paper and sketched out the general layout of the terrain and obstacles, keeping the game mechanic in mind. I&rsquo;d then build the level using the <a href="/2015/02/08/building-a-level-editor-in-html5/">level editor</a> and test it on the laptop (with play-testing coming later on mobile). In hind-sight, it would have been nicer to set up an easier deploy process to prototype a section of level and test on the fly via mobile, but that&rsquo;s really a lesson learned for next time.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/design_doc.jpg' width='' height='' title='The layout of one of the later levels for Cosmic Badger'><span class='caption-text'>The layout of one of the later levels for Cosmic Badger</span></span></p>

<p>I wanted 7 distinct stages with 3 levels per stage, so I came up with a list of themes that might be cool. Out of those themes I picked my favourite according to how varied I could make the obstacles and how interesting I could make the tilesheets. The list was stripped down to the following -</p>

<ul>
<li>Grassy / forest</li>
<li>Snow</li>
<li>Industrial</li>
<li>Toy room</li>
<li>Black &amp; White</li>
<li>Asian / oriental</li>
<li>Some crazy checkered terrain stage that I didn&rsquo;t have any specific label for (this was more based off a random sketch that I did)</li>
</ul>


<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/badger_kingdom_sketch.jpg' width='' height='' title='The initial concept art of that same later level'><span class='caption-text'>The initial concept art of that same later level</span></span></p>

<p>I started sketching the ideas on a notebook, which then became a strong basis for how the sprites would evolve during game development. Photos were taken of the images and then inked/edited on the computer to become proper sprites. The images weren&rsquo;t perfect by any means, but they were legible enough to fit in an indie game, and something that I would later improve upon with practice (I&rsquo;ll show some examples of that evolution in a later post). This notebook became a bit of a bible during development. I know you&rsquo;re dying to see how this actually turned out, which is why it&rsquo;s being covered in the next post.</p>

<p>What process do you have for designing your levels? Add your insights in the comments below.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[When to pivot on a game idea]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/2015/02/15/knowing-when-to-cut-the-scope-of-your-indie-game/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-15T20:53:54+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/2015/02/15/knowing-when-to-cut-the-scope-of-your-indie-game</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s not uncommon for indie developers to be working on a game when fresh ideas/features start to interrupt their train of thought. But what happens when an entirely new game concept altogether manifests itself? Do you scribble it down and carry on until you&rsquo;re finished your current project, or is the idea so captivating that you <em>just</em> can&rsquo;t wait to work on it, ditching your work in progress? This exact scenario happened to me during my first game, so I&rsquo;d like to take the opportunity to explain the path that was taken and the reasoning behind it.</p>

<p><strong>The road so far</strong></p>

<p>As <a href="/2015/02/05/technical-implementation-of-a-html5-game/">previously mentioned</a>, my game engine was up and running and now work could finally begin on the design of the ballon game. Five weeks had already gone by of the original estimated 2-3 month project so this was a good time to do a roadmap check. The following were the key points that needed to be achieved in the next month:</p>

<ul>
<li>Tilesheets to cover roughly 12 levels</li>
<li>Design the levels to sprawl over both X and Y axises</li>
<li>Enemies with different behaviour to make the game challenging and varied over the levels</li>
<li>Sound effects for enemies, weapons, the player, etc.</li>
<li>Music for all the levels</li>
<li>Some sort of storage to track progress, collectables, etc.</li>
<li>A menu system for selecting levels, pausing, etc.</li>
<li>Design tutorials for the start of the game</li>
</ul>


<p>The first thing that became apparent was that most of this would <em>not</em> be achievable in just a couple of months. The biggest hurdles would be designing the levels and creating the tilesheets for everything, I wasn&rsquo;t even so worried about the coding. This was never going to work, and as <a href="/2015/02/12/top-9-tips-for-indie-developers/">advised in the last post</a> I needed  to cut my scope drastically to meet my deadline, but what could be cut? As far as I could see this wasn&rsquo;t going to be possible unless I released just a couple of levels. That just wouldn&rsquo;t cut it for the app store. Thankfully there was a backup plan that [in my mind] was achievable in this small amount of time.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/balloon_game.gif' width='' height='' title='The balloon game as it currently looked'><span class='caption-text'>The balloon game as it currently looked</span></span></p>

<p><strong>A new game idea</strong></p>

<p>One routine I had gotten into the habit of doing was to leave a notepad by my bed at night. I&rsquo;ve always been a little bit of an insomniac and when I&rsquo;m lying in bed after putting in a 10 hour day of game coding my mind was always racing with ideas. Sometimes the thoughts that came to me were just tasks that I had forgotten to take into account, other times they were new gameplay mechanics, enemies, puzzles, etc.</p>

<p>One night, lying in bed, the completely unrelated thought of using portals in a game popped into my head. Now it&rsquo;s not like this is a revolutionary idea by any means, but after some brief app store searching I came to the conclusion that this hadn&rsquo;t been implemented in the mobile space to great effect. I had this idea of a platformer/auto-runner where your character had to teleport around obstacles. I switched the light on, wrote it down in my notepad and went back to bed.</p>

<p>With the burden of the scope on my current project, the next day I was keen to prototype my new idea and see if it was any fun to play. I chopped the balloons off my character and used my first crappy tile sheet (effectively some sort of hexagon manhole cover?) to create  an auto-scrolling level. I had to add the auto scrolling, change the game mechanic and controls to use portals instead, and then add gravity to the game so the player could fall onto the terrain. This was the finished prototype and the idea was surprisingly fresh and fun to play.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/early_cosmic_badger.gif' width='' height='' title='The game after the idea pivot and the first Cosmic Badger prototype'><span class='caption-text'>The game after the idea pivot and the first Cosmic Badger prototype</span></span></p>

<p><strong>The road beyond</strong></p>

<p>This new game concept was going to be a <em>lot</em>  easier to implement. It was an auto-runner so the level design could be constrained to the x-axis (like the early Mario games) and there was no need to add different enemy behaviours (at least for the minimum viable product). Design-wise, the balloon game was a much more interesting project to me, but realistically it would take too long. I decided that for my first project I needed to start small, and pivoted to the new portal project.</p>

<p><strong>The message to all other indie devs</strong></p>

<p>Im sure there&rsquo;s a graveyard of unfinished titles sitting on different developers&#8217; hard drives, simply because they were too ambitious, or maybe because that person got bored before they could finish it. Pick a project that&rsquo;s achievable given your timeframe and if it&rsquo;s possible, cut your scope down to a minimal game. You don&rsquo;t necessarily have to sacrifice the quality of the game but a basic game on an app store is better than no game at all.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
