<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: canvas | The story of Cosmic Badger]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/categories/canvas/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-30T21:14:50+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Reilly]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Back from sabbatical]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/2015/08/30/back-from-sabbatical/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-30T20:01:46+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/2015/08/30/back-from-sabbatical</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For anyone following previous posts, you may have noticed a distinct lack of activity for a long time. This has mainly come down to a couple things:</p>

<p><strong> 1. Launch Frenzy </strong></p>

<p>Launching a game is stressful business, you gotta create press kits, draft press emails, register as a business owner, taxes and a whole lot of other boring adult stuff.</p>

<p><strong> 2. Burnout </strong></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve spent the good part of two years plugging away at this little project on evenings and weekends. I&rsquo;ve missed an Australian Summer (as an Irish person, that&rsquo;s quite a sacrifice) confined to a text editor, chasing the idea of seeing a game through to completion. When I had the realisation that I wasn&rsquo;t an overnight millionaire post-launch, I decided to take a step back and enjoy my freedom for a while.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve finally been able to read again, play video games (I might finally complete GTA) and staying out late on a weekend. While all of this has been great, there&rsquo;s unfinished business. I&rsquo;ve created a playable game and have received some good [albeit mixed in a few circumstances] feedback on it but it&rsquo;s still missing some finishing touches. It&rsquo;s time to give it one last go before moving on to new projects.</p>

<p>More blog posts coming soon!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bringing sketches to life]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/2015/03/20/bringing-game-dev-sketches-to-life/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-20T22:57:13+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/2015/03/20/bringing-game-dev-sketches-to-life</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There&rsquo;s nothing more satisfying as an indie dev than sketching down an idea and then implementing that idea in your game world. In this post I wanted to pay tribute to some of the earlier sketches and how they turned out, being implemented in the Cosmic Badger universe.</p>

<p>The grass stage were the first levels that I worked on. I had very little experience as a &ldquo;pixel artist&rdquo; at this point and I actually went through a couple of iterations of the sprites before I got it to a state that I was happy with. I&rsquo;ll cover some of those in another blog.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/grass_stage.jpg' width='' height='' title='Concept art for the grass themed stage'><span class='caption-text'>Concept art for the grass themed stage</span></span></p>

<p>The industrial stage took a day or two to complete the background for. I hadn&rsquo;t really gotten a grasp on gradients at this stage and was changing the variation in shadow manually by changing the brightness/contrast. Everything was very much a learning process.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/industrial_stage.jpg' width='' height='' title='Concept art for the industrial themed stage'><span class='caption-text'>Concept art for the industrial themed stage</span></span></p>

<p>Despite its simplicity, the toy stage came out as one of the best. The varying colours made it much more of an interesting level, landscape-wise. Some of the sketches were crudley drawn and then done properly from scratch on computer, others were scanned and then inked.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/toy_stage.jpg' width='' height='' title='Concept art for the toy stage. Some of these sprites are still a little rough as I never re-touched them later. I&rsquo;ll get to them.'><span class='caption-text'>Concept art for the toy stage. Some of these sprites are still a little rough as I never re-touched them later. I&rsquo;ll get to them.</span></span></p>

<p>The black and white levels were some of the hardest to get just right. The foreground obstacles had to contrast enough from the background to be visible but that&rsquo;s kind of hard when you&rsquo;re working with the different tones of the same colour all the time.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/black_and_white_stage.jpg' width='' height='' title='This came out as one of my favourites'><span class='caption-text'>This came out as one of my favourites</span></span></p>

<p>How much has your own concept art reflected your final game? Could it still be improved or are you happy with the results?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Level design of an indie game]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/2015/02/26/designing-levels-for-a-2d-platformer/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-26T20:36:37+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/2015/02/26/designing-levels-for-a-2d-platformer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Designing your game is probably one of the most crucial parts of the game development lifecycle. It&rsquo;s an iterative process, for sure, but design documents have to start somewhere. In this post I&rsquo;m going to talk about the initial designs of the levels in Cosmic Badger and the inception of the tilesheets used in the game to date.</p>

<p>With a <a href="/2015/02/15/knowing-when-to-cut-the-scope-of-your-indie-game/">clearer vision</a> of how the game would look, it was now time to start designing the levels. There was no real complex workflow to this. I bought a load of graph paper and sketched out the general layout of the terrain and obstacles, keeping the game mechanic in mind. I&rsquo;d then build the level using the <a href="/2015/02/08/building-a-level-editor-in-html5/">level editor</a> and test it on the laptop (with play-testing coming later on mobile). In hind-sight, it would have been nicer to set up an easier deploy process to prototype a section of level and test on the fly via mobile, but that&rsquo;s really a lesson learned for next time.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/design_doc.jpg' width='' height='' title='The layout of one of the later levels for Cosmic Badger'><span class='caption-text'>The layout of one of the later levels for Cosmic Badger</span></span></p>

<p>I wanted 7 distinct stages with 3 levels per stage, so I came up with a list of themes that might be cool. Out of those themes I picked my favourite according to how varied I could make the obstacles and how interesting I could make the tilesheets. The list was stripped down to the following -</p>

<ul>
<li>Grassy / forest</li>
<li>Snow</li>
<li>Industrial</li>
<li>Toy room</li>
<li>Black &amp; White</li>
<li>Asian / oriental</li>
<li>Some crazy checkered terrain stage that I didn&rsquo;t have any specific label for (this was more based off a random sketch that I did)</li>
</ul>


<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/badger_kingdom_sketch.jpg' width='' height='' title='The initial concept art of that same later level'><span class='caption-text'>The initial concept art of that same later level</span></span></p>

<p>I started sketching the ideas on a notebook, which then became a strong basis for how the sprites would evolve during game development. Photos were taken of the images and then inked/edited on the computer to become proper sprites. The images weren&rsquo;t perfect by any means, but they were legible enough to fit in an indie game, and something that I would later improve upon with practice (I&rsquo;ll show some examples of that evolution in a later post). This notebook became a bit of a bible during development. I know you&rsquo;re dying to see how this actually turned out, which is why it&rsquo;s being covered in the next post.</p>

<p>What process do you have for designing your levels? Add your insights in the comments below.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[When to pivot on a game idea]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/2015/02/15/knowing-when-to-cut-the-scope-of-your-indie-game/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-15T20:53:54+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/2015/02/15/knowing-when-to-cut-the-scope-of-your-indie-game</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s not uncommon for indie developers to be working on a game when fresh ideas/features start to interrupt their train of thought. But what happens when an entirely new game concept altogether manifests itself? Do you scribble it down and carry on until you&rsquo;re finished your current project, or is the idea so captivating that you <em>just</em> can&rsquo;t wait to work on it, ditching your work in progress? This exact scenario happened to me during my first game, so I&rsquo;d like to take the opportunity to explain the path that was taken and the reasoning behind it.</p>

<p><strong>The road so far</strong></p>

<p>As <a href="/2015/02/05/technical-implementation-of-a-html5-game/">previously mentioned</a>, my game engine was up and running and now work could finally begin on the design of the ballon game. Five weeks had already gone by of the original estimated 2-3 month project so this was a good time to do a roadmap check. The following were the key points that needed to be achieved in the next month:</p>

<ul>
<li>Tilesheets to cover roughly 12 levels</li>
<li>Design the levels to sprawl over both X and Y axises</li>
<li>Enemies with different behaviour to make the game challenging and varied over the levels</li>
<li>Sound effects for enemies, weapons, the player, etc.</li>
<li>Music for all the levels</li>
<li>Some sort of storage to track progress, collectables, etc.</li>
<li>A menu system for selecting levels, pausing, etc.</li>
<li>Design tutorials for the start of the game</li>
</ul>


<p>The first thing that became apparent was that most of this would <em>not</em> be achievable in just a couple of months. The biggest hurdles would be designing the levels and creating the tilesheets for everything, I wasn&rsquo;t even so worried about the coding. This was never going to work, and as <a href="/2015/02/12/top-9-tips-for-indie-developers/">advised in the last post</a> I needed  to cut my scope drastically to meet my deadline, but what could be cut? As far as I could see this wasn&rsquo;t going to be possible unless I released just a couple of levels. That just wouldn&rsquo;t cut it for the app store. Thankfully there was a backup plan that [in my mind] was achievable in this small amount of time.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/balloon_game.gif' width='' height='' title='The balloon game as it currently looked'><span class='caption-text'>The balloon game as it currently looked</span></span></p>

<p><strong>A new game idea</strong></p>

<p>One routine I had gotten into the habit of doing was to leave a notepad by my bed at night. I&rsquo;ve always been a little bit of an insomniac and when I&rsquo;m lying in bed after putting in a 10 hour day of game coding my mind was always racing with ideas. Sometimes the thoughts that came to me were just tasks that I had forgotten to take into account, other times they were new gameplay mechanics, enemies, puzzles, etc.</p>

<p>One night, lying in bed, the completely unrelated thought of using portals in a game popped into my head. Now it&rsquo;s not like this is a revolutionary idea by any means, but after some brief app store searching I came to the conclusion that this hadn&rsquo;t been implemented in the mobile space to great effect. I had this idea of a platformer/auto-runner where your character had to teleport around obstacles. I switched the light on, wrote it down in my notepad and went back to bed.</p>

<p>With the burden of the scope on my current project, the next day I was keen to prototype my new idea and see if it was any fun to play. I chopped the balloons off my character and used my first crappy tile sheet (effectively some sort of hexagon manhole cover?) to create  an auto-scrolling level. I had to add the auto scrolling, change the game mechanic and controls to use portals instead, and then add gravity to the game so the player could fall onto the terrain. This was the finished prototype and the idea was surprisingly fresh and fun to play.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/early_cosmic_badger.gif' width='' height='' title='The game after the idea pivot and the first Cosmic Badger prototype'><span class='caption-text'>The game after the idea pivot and the first Cosmic Badger prototype</span></span></p>

<p><strong>The road beyond</strong></p>

<p>This new game concept was going to be a <em>lot</em>  easier to implement. It was an auto-runner so the level design could be constrained to the x-axis (like the early Mario games) and there was no need to add different enemy behaviours (at least for the minimum viable product). Design-wise, the balloon game was a much more interesting project to me, but realistically it would take too long. I decided that for my first project I needed to start small, and pivoted to the new portal project.</p>

<p><strong>The message to all other indie devs</strong></p>

<p>Im sure there&rsquo;s a graveyard of unfinished titles sitting on different developers&#8217; hard drives, simply because they were too ambitious, or maybe because that person got bored before they could finish it. Pick a project that&rsquo;s achievable given your timeframe and if it&rsquo;s possible, cut your scope down to a minimal game. You don&rsquo;t necessarily have to sacrifice the quality of the game but a basic game on an app store is better than no game at all.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Top 9 tips for indie game developers]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/2015/02/12/top-9-tips-for-indie-developers/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-12T20:42:20+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.cosmicbadger.com/2015/02/12/top-9-tips-for-indie-developers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Two years ago I started prototyping a html5 game as a side-project while I was in between jobs. Today that project has evolved into a complete game and now it&rsquo;s roughly [&hellip;hopefully] about a month away from app store submission. Over that time I&rsquo;ve come up with a lot of advice that I wish my past self knew when I started and I want to share that information with new and experienced indie developers alike.</p>

<p><strong>1. Don’t design everything at once, play-test early and often</strong></p>

<p>This is really something that tripped me up. This may have not happened to everyone, but I&rsquo;m sure others have encountered it too. I spent a <em>long</em> time designing my levels up front without properly play-testing them one-by-one first. I found that once I had become familiar with the game mechanic and difficulty of one level, the other levels were a little tedious and I had to design all of the levels again, causing a <em>lot</em> of wasted time and effort. Play-test your level the minute you&rsquo;ve finished designing it, it may influence how the rest of the game evolves.</p>

<p><strong>2. Ask for feedback</strong></p>

<p>I’ve seen some great games that have been shared on Reddit and IndieDB (I mean, what the hell is <a href="http://www.indiedb.com/games/push-me-pull-you">this</a>?). Some of which started as a rough concept and then evolved into a great idea by user suggestions. We&rsquo;re not all product managers or professional game designers - ask the public what they want, don&rsquo;t tell them what they want.</p>

<p><strong>3. Be humble</strong></p>

<p>This is a follow up on the previous point. I posted a few images of my game on Imgur and Reddit a while back to get some public response. Some people criticised a few of the backgrounds saying that they were too simple or boring. Initially I was a bit annoyed because I&rsquo;m not a sprite artist and it was the best I could do, but I had to really take a step back and put myself in the mind of the consumer. Are people really going to pay money for a game that is sub-standard given everything else on the market right now? Get feedback, but try not to rubbish people&rsquo;s opinions simply because they&rsquo;re negative or not constructive. Try to take something out of it and don&rsquo;t take it too personally.</p>

<p><strong>4. Decrease your scope</strong></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s great to have so many ideas that you want to implement but that doesn&rsquo;t really matter if you have nothing on any app store to show for it. Start with a minimum viable product and iterate on new ideas later. Chances are that someone playing your game might even suggest a better improvement than your original ideas.</p>

<p><strong>5. Give yourself some time off</strong></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m just going to go ahead and make the assumption that the majority of people reading this will be indie developers working on a personal project outside of their daytime job. Setting goals and deadlines for your game is important, but so is the need to re-energise. I&rsquo;ve rage quit a couple of times and then ditched my game development from a period of weeks to months, simply because I never took a break. Chances are that extra two hours you spent awake last night didn&rsquo;t take much of a chunk off your work. You probably even may have introduced bugs because you were burt out. Watch TV, take your dog for a walk, or just go to the pub for a pint. The work will still be there tomorrow.</p>

<p><strong>6. Ask for help</strong></p>

<p>When I started working on my game I had an stubborn sense of pride regarding doing absolutely everything and being able to claim the credit for it, but we can’t be good at everything. If you know a someone that&rsquo;s good at making sprites then ask them if they can help improve on what you have, ask someone to make music for your game or make a trailer for your app store.</p>

<p><strong>7. Estimate work for each task and then multiply it by five</strong></p>

<p>This isn&rsquo;t really an indie dev problem but a software dev problem. Have you ever said that some new feature was easy to implement and would only take a few hours only to still be swearing at it a week later? I remember telling my work colleagues last September that there were roughly three weeks before I was ready for release. It&rsquo;s now February and I still have bugs to fix and marketing to do before submitting to the app store. Moral of the story, be realistic with effort involved and how much free time you&rsquo;ll actually have on weekends/evenings.</p>

<p><strong>8. <em>Give</em> feedback and engage with the community</strong></p>

<p>Some people might feel like they&rsquo;re fighting an up-hill battle with so much competition out there, but the way I see it is that there&rsquo;s AAA game studios and then there&rsquo;s us. We&rsquo;re not really in competition with each other and there&rsquo;s so many awesome ideas out there that just need a little re-enforcement. Engage with other indie devs on Reddit or any other forums. Tell them how they can improve their idea/gameplay/trailer/marketing, or just tell them that you like what they&rsquo;re doing and to stick with it. You&rsquo;d be surprised how far it goes, it may even give someone the motivation to keep going when they&rsquo;re doubting their own work.</p>

<p><strong>9. Know when to call it a day</strong></p>

<p>I think that most developers can relate to the fact that there&rsquo;s <em>always</em> something that still needs to go into their game, but if it&rsquo;s playable now and it&rsquo;s actually a game now then why not just release it and push the update later? Great things happen in the arena, not when you&rsquo;re in the stands.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s just a few things that resonated the most for me. Can you relate to any of them? What advice can you give from your own experiences?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
